so first
let's discuss about how do we define a
single layer
of a graph neural network right so what
what goes
into a single layer a single layer has
two components
it has a component of a message
transformation
and it has a component of message
aggregation and as i mentioned
different graph neural network
architectures basically differ in how
these operations uh are being done uh
among other other kind of things that uh
differ between them
so what is the idea of a single gnn
layer the idea is that we want to
compress
a set of messages a set of vectors
coming from the children
from the you know from the bottom layer
of the neural network
in some sense compress them by
aggregating them and we are going to
to do this as a two-step process as a
message transformation and message
aggregation right so if we think about
this
we are getting a set of children at the
at the bottom a set of inputs
we have we have an output what we have
to do is
take the message from each of the child
and transform it
then we have to aggregate these messages
into a single message
and pass it on so the way you can think
of this is that we get
messages denoted as circles here from
the three neighbors
from the previous layer we also have our
own
message right message of the node v from
the previous layer
somehow we want to combine this
information um to create the next level
embedding or the next level message for
this node
of interest what is important here to
note is that this is a set
so the ordering in which we are
aggregating these messages from the
children
is not important or is arbitrary
and for this reason these aggregation
functions
that aggregate that summarize that uh
compress
in some sense the messages coming from
the children have to be order invariant
because
they shouldn't depend you know in which
ordering
am i considering the neighbors because
there is no special ordering to the
neighbors
to the lower level to the children in
the uh
in the network that's an important uh
important detail
of course another important detail is
that we want to combine information
coming from the neighbor
from the neighbors together with node's
own information
from the previous layer as denoted here
so you know i'm connecting information
from level l minus one
to create a message at level l and i'm
collecting information from the
neighbors
from the previous layer as well as from
the representation of that node itself
uh at the previous uh layer so let me
now make things a bit more
uh uh precise so we will talk about
message computation
as a first uh operation that we need to
decide
and basically the message computation
takes the representation of the node
at the previous layer and somehow
transforms
transforms it into this message message
information so
each note creates a message with which
will be sent to
other nodes in the next layer an example
of a simple message transformation is
that you take the
previous layer embedding of a node and
multiply it
uh with the matrix w so this is a simple
linear layer
linear transformation uh and this is you
know what we talked about
uh in the previous uh lecture right so
that's the
that's the first part and we need to
decide this message function in this
case is simply this matrix multiply
the second question is about aggregation
the intuition here is that each node
will aggregate the messages
from its neighbors so the idea is that i
take now this transformed messages
m that we just defined on the previous
slide right so i take these transformed
messages
coming from nodes you from the previous
level that i transformed let's say in
this case with w
and i wanna aggregate them into a single
message
right i want to take this thing and kind
of compress it aggregate it
what are some examples of aggregation
functions a summation
is a simple aggregation function an
average
is a order invariant aggregation
function as well as for
example max we take the maximum message
or the
maximum coordinate wise value and that's
how we aggregate and again
all this all these aggregation functions
are
order invariant so for example one
concrete way how you could do this is to
say uh-huh
the level l embedding for node v
is simply a summation of the transformed
uh
messages coming from the neighbors uh u
of that node of interest v
and you know this is where the messages
from previous layer got transformed and
now we simply sum them up
to have the uh to have the embedding for
the
node at level l and of course now this
know that level l to
send to to create a message for level l
plus one
it will take now wl plus one multiply it
with
h and send it to whoever is is above
them
uh in the graph neural network uh
structure
so this was now a message uh
operation message transformation and
message
aggregation one important issue is
if you do it the way i define it so far
is that information from the node itself
could get lost right basically that
computation
of uh message for level for node v for
level l
does not directly depend on what we have
already computed
uh for for that node same node v from
the previous level
right so for example if i do it simply
as i show here we are
simply aggregating information about
neighbors but we don't really say
okay but who is this node v what do we
know about node v before
so um an opportunity here is to actually
um to include the previous level
embedding of node v
when we are computing the embedding of v
for the next level
so usually basically a different message
computation
will be performed right what what do i
mean by this is for example the
message transformation matrix w will be
applied to the neighbor's u
while there be a different message
aggregation function b
uh that will uh be applied to the
embedding of node
v itself so that's the first difference
um right so that the message of it from
the node itself
from previous layer will be multiplied
by b while messages from
neighbors from previous layer are going
to be multiplied by
w and then the second difference is that
after
aggregating from neighbors we can
aggregate messages
from v itself as well and usually this
is done via concatenation or a summation
so to show you an example the way we can
we can do this is to say aha i'm taking
my messages
from neighbors and i'm aggregating them
let's say with a
with a summation operator i'm taking the
message from v
itself uh multiple right like like i
define it up here
and then i'm going to concatenate these
two messages simply like concatenate
them one
next to each other and that's my next
layer embedding for node v
so simply i'm saying i'm aggregating
information from neighbors
plus retaining the information about the
node
uh that i already had and this is now a
way how to
uh keep track of the information that
the node has already computed about
itself
so that it doesn't get lost through the
layers of
propagation it's let's say by
concatenation here or
by uh summation that's another popular
choice
so putting all this together what did we
learn
we learned that we have this message
where each node
from the previous layer takes its own
embedding its own information
transforms it and sends it sends it up
to the parent
this is denoted here through this
message transformation function
usually this is simply a linear function
like a matrix multiply
and then we have this message
aggregation step
where we aggregate transformed messages
from the neighbors right so we take
these messages
m that we have computed here and we
aggregate them
we aggregate them with an average with a
summation
or with a maximum pooling type approach
and then what we can also do is
another extension here is to also add a
self message and concatenate it
and then after we have done all this we
pass this through a non-linearity
through a non-linear
activation function and this last step
is important
because it adds expressiveness often
you know this non-linearity is written
as sigma
in reality this can be a rectified
linear unit or a sigmoid
or any other specific type of um
nonlinear activation function popular in
other types of
neural networks as well but that's
essentially how a single layer
of a graph neural network looks like
so now that we have seen this in
abstract i want to mention
some of the seminal graph neural network
architectures that have been developed
and kind of interpret them in this
unified
message transformation message
aggregation
framework so last lecture we talked
about
graph convolutional neural network or a
gcn
and i've wrote this equation i said aha
the
the information the embedding of node v
at layer l is simply an average of the
embeddings of uh uh of
nodes u that are neighbors of v
normalized by the
by the in degree of node v and
transformed transformed with matrix w
and
sent through a non-linearity so now the
question is
how can i take this equation that i've
written here and write it in this
message transformation plus aggregation
function and the way you
can you can do this is simply take this
w and distribute it
in it inside so basically now um
w times h divided by number of neighbors
is the message transformation function
and then the message aggregation
function is simply a summation and then
we have a non-linearity here so this is
what a graph convolutional
neural network is in terms of message
aggregation
and message transformation um
so to write it even more explicitly each
neighbor transforms the message by
saying
i take my uh previous layer embedding
multiplied with w
and divided by the node degree of v so
uh this is normal normalization by node
degree and then the aggregation is a
summation
over the neighbors uh of node v and then
applying uh a non-linearity activation
function here
denoted as sigma so this is now a
gcn written as a message transformation
and a message aggregation type operation
so that's um number uh the first
classical architecture the second
architecture i want to mention
is called graph sage and graph sage
builds builds upon the gcn
but extends it in several important
aspects uh the first aspect is that it
realizes that this
aggregation function is an arbitrary
aggregation function so it allows for
multiple different choices of
aggregation functions
not only averaging and the second thing
is it it
talks about taking the message from the
node itself
uh transforming it and then
concatenating it with the aggregating
aggregated messages which adds a lot of
expressive
power so now let's write the graph sage
equation in this message plus uh
aggregation
type operations right message is
computed through the
uh aggregation operator agg here um and
the way we can think of this is that
this is kind of a two-stage approach
first is that um we
we take the individual messages um and
transform them let's say through
linear operations then we apply the
aggregation operator that basically
gives me now a summary of the messages
coming from the neighbors
and then the second important step now
is that i take
the messages coming from the neighbors
already aggregated
i concatenate it with these own
message or embedding from the previous
layer
concatenate these two together multiply
them with uh with the transformation
matrix
and pass through a non-linearity right
so the differences
between gcn is here and another more
important difference is here that we are
concatenating and taking
our own embedding as well
so um to now to say what kind of
aggregation functions can we use
we can simply take for example weighted
average of neighbors
which is what gcn is doing
we can for example take any kind of
pulling which is uh you know
take the take the transform the neighbor
vectors and apply a
symmetric uh vector function like a min
or a max
so you could even have for example here
as a transformation you don't have to
have a linear transformation you could
have a multi-layer
perceptron as a message transformation
function and then an aggregation
you can also not take the average of the
messages but you sum up
the messages and uh this different
aggregation functions have different
theoretical properties
and we are going to actually talk about
the theoretical properties and
consequences
of the choice of the aggregation
function on the expressive power
of the model in one of the future
lectures
and what you could even do if you like
is you could apply an lstm so basically
you could apply a sequence
model uh to the to the messages coming
from the neighbors
um and here the important thing is that
a sequence model
is not order invariant so when you train
it you wanna permute the orderings
so that the you teach the the sequence
model not to keep
uh kind of to ignore uh the ordering of
the messages that it receives
but you could use something like this um
as a
uh as an aggregation uh uh operator so
a lot of freedom uh to choose here
and then the last thing to mention about
graph sage
is that adds this notion of l2
normalization
so the idea is that we want to apply l
to the embeddings at every layer and
when i say l2 normalization
all i mean by that is we want to measure
the distance
some of the squared values of the
entries of the embedding of a given
of a given node take the square root of
that and then divide by the distance so
basically this means that the euclidean
length
of this embedding vector will always be
equal to one
and sometimes this is quite important
and leads to big
performance improvement because without
l2 normalization
the embedding vectors of nodes can have
different scales different lengths
and in some cases normalization of the
embedding
results in performance improvement so
after l2 normalization step as i
introduced it here all vectors will have
the same
l2 norm they'll have the same length
which is the length of
one this is how this is defined
if if you want to really see it so l2
normalization is also an important
component
when deciding on the design decisions
on the specific architecture of the
graph neural network
and then the last uh classical
architecture
that i want to talk about is called
graph attention network
and here we are going to learn uh this
concept of an
attention so let me first tell you what
a graph attention network is and then i
will
define the notion of attention and
how do we learn it and what what it
intuitively means
so the motivation is the following
writing graph attention
network when we are aggregating messages
from the neighbors
we have a weight um associated
with every neighbor right so for every
neighbor u
of node v we have a weight alpha
and this weight we call a tension weight
and the idea is that this weight can now
tell me
how important of a neighbor is
a given is a given node or in some sense
how much attention to pay
to a given ma to a message from a given
node u
because if these weights are different
then messages from different nodes
will have different weight in this
summation
that's the idea so now let's make a step
back
explain why why how how this is
motivated
why it's a good idea and how to uh learn
these weights
so if you think about the two
architectures we talked about so far
so the gcn and graph sage there
is already an implicit notion of this
alpha
so alpha uv is simply one over the
degree of node v
so basically this is a weight factor or
an importance of a message coming from
you
for the node v and uh
so far you know this alpha was defined
implicitly
um and we can actually define it
um more explicitly or we can actually
learn it
in our case alpha was actually for all
the uh
incoming no nodes u alpha was the same
it only depended on the degree
of node v but didn't really depend on
the u itself so it was a very limiting
kind of notion of attention right so in
in graph sage or
gcn all neighbors are equally important
to node v
when aggregating messages and the
question is can we kind of
generalize this can we generalize this
so that we learn how important
is a message from a given node uh to the
node that is aggregating messages right
so you want to learn
message importances and this notion of
an importance is called attention and
attention
the word attention is kind of inspired
by the by
in a sense with cognitive attention
right so attention
alpha focuses on the important parts of
the input data
and kind of fades out or ignores the
rest
so the idea is that the neural network
should devote more computing power
more attention to that small important
part of the
input um and perhaps you know ignore
choose to ignore the rest
um and which part of the data is more
important
depends on the context and the idea is
that we are going to learn
what part of the data is important
through the
model training process so we allow the
model to learn
importance of different uh of different
pieces of input that it is
uh receiving so in our case we would
want to learn this
attention weight that will tell us how
important is a message coming from
node u to this uh node
v and we want this attention of course
depend on the
u as well as on v as well
so the question is right how do we learn
uh this uh attention weights these
weighting factors
uh alpha so the goal is to specify
an arbitrary importance uh between
um between neighbors when we do message
aggregation
and the idea is that we can compute the
embedding of each node in the graph
following this attention strategies
where nodes attend over the
messages coming from the neighborhood by
attend i mean give different
importances to them and then we are
going to
implicitly specify different weights to
different nodes uh in the neighborhood
and we are going to learn
these weights these importances
the way we are going to do this is uh to
compute this
as a byproduct of the attention
mechanism or we are going to define this
notion of attention mechanism
that is going to give us this attention
scores or attention weights
so let's let us think about this
attention uh mechanism a
by first computing attention
coefficients
e uh vu across pairs of nodes uh u and v
based on their messages so the idea
would be that i want to define some
function a
that will take the embedding of node u
at previous layer
embedding of node v at previous layer
perhaps transform these two embeddings
and then take this as input and pro give
me a weight
right and this weight will tell me the
importance of
uh use message on the uh
on the node v so for example just to be
concrete right if i wanna say
what is the attention coefficients e a
b it's simply some function a of the
embedding of node a at the previous step
uh and the embedding of node b
at the previous step at the previous
layer of the graph neural network
and this will give me now the weight of
this uh
or importance of this particular edge
so now that i have these coefficients i
want to normalize them
to get the final attention weight so
what do i mean by
for example uh normalize is that we can
apply
a soft max function uh to them so that
these attention weights are going to sum
to one so i take the coefficients e
that we have just defined i uh
exponentiated them
and then you know divide by this
exponentiated sum of them
so that uh this uh attention weights uh
alpha now are going to sum to one and
then
right when i'm doing message aggregation
i can now do a waste
weighted sum based on the attention
weights uh
alpha so here are the alphas these are
these alphas
that depend on e and e is the uh
is the is depends on the previous layer
and bearings of nodes
u and v so for example if i now say how
would aggregation for node a look like
the way i would do this is i would
compute this attention weights uh
alpha a b alpha ac and alpha a d because
bc and d are its neighbors this alphas
would be computed as
as i show up here they will be computed
by previous layer
embeddings of these nodes on the
endpoints of the edge
and then my aggregation function is
simply a wasted average
of the messages coming from the
neighbors where
message is multiplied
by the weight alpha that we have
computed
and defined up here so that's um
basically the idea of the attention
mechanism
um now what is the form of this
attention mechanism a we still haven't
decided
how embedding of one node and embedding
of the other node get
get combined computed into this uh
weight e the way it is usually done
is uh um you you have many different
choices like you could
use a simple linear layer one layer
neural network to do this or have
alpha this function a have trainable
parameters
uh so for example a a popular choice is
to simply to say
let me take the embeddings of nodes a
and b are the previous layer
perhaps let me transform them let me
concatenate them and then
apply a linear layer to them and that
will give me this weight
eab to which then i can apply soft max
and then based on that soft max
transformed weight
i use that weight as a in the
aggregation function
and the important point is that these
parameters of of uh
function a this attention mechanism a
basically parameters of these functions
are trained jointly
so we learn the parameters of the
attention mechanism
together with the weight matrices so
message transformation matrices
in the message aggregation step so we do
all this training
in an end-to-end fashion
what this means in practice is that
working with this type of attention
mechanisms
can be tricky because this can be quite
finicky
uh in a sense maybe sometimes it's hard
to learn
hard to make it converge so what we can
also
do is uh to expand this notion of
attention
to what is called a multi-head attention
and multi-head attention is a way to
stabilize learning
process of the attention mechanism and
the idea is quite simple the idea is
that we'll have
multiple attention scores so we are
going to have multiple attention
mechanisms a
um and each one and we are going to
train learn all of them
uh simultaneously so the idea is that
we would have different functions a for
example in this case we would have three
different functions a
which means i would we would get three
different uh
attention coefficients attention weights
for a given edge
vu and then we will do the
aggregation three times get the
aggregated messages from the neighbors
and now we can
further aggregate uh these messages
into a single uh aggregated message and
the point here is now
that we when we learn these functions a1
a2 a3
we are going to randomly initialize
parameters of each one of them
and through the learning process each
one of them is kind of going to converge
to some local minima but
because we are using multiple of them
and we are averaging
their transformations together this will
basically allow
our model to to be to be more robust
it will allow our learning process not
to get stuck
in some weird part of the optimization
space
um and kind of it will work better
on the average so the idea of this
multi-head attention is
is simple to summarize is that we are
going to have
multiple attention weights on the on the
same edge
and we are going to use them uh
separately in message aggregation
and then the final message that we get
for for uh
for a node will be simply the
aggregation like the average
of this individual attention-based uh
aggregations
one important detail here is that each
of these different
alphas has to be predicted with a
different
function a and each of these functions a
has to be initialized
with a random uh different set of
starting parameters so that each one
gets a chance to kind of converge to
some uh local
minima that's the idea and that adds to
the
robustness and stabilizes uh the
learning process
so this is what i wanted to say about
the attention mechanism and how do we
define it
so next let me define let me discuss a
bit
the benefits of the attention mechanism
and the
key benefit is that this allows
implicitly for specifying
different importance values to different
neighbors
um it is computationally efficient in a
sense that
computation of attention coefficient can
be
parallelized across all the incoming
messages right for every incoming
message i compute
the attention weight by applying
function a
that only depends on the embedding of
one node and the embedding of the other
node
in the previous layer so this is good
it is in some sense storage efficiency
because
a sparse matrix operators do not require
too many non-zero elements basically i
need one entry per node
and one entry per edge so
you know that's cheap that's linear in
the amount of data we have
and it has a fixed number of parameters
meaning the
mesh the the attention mechanism
function a
has a fixed number of parameters that is
independent of the graph size
another important aspect is that
attention weights are localized
they attend to local network
neighborhoods so basically allow
tell you what part of the neighborhood
to focus on
and they generalize meaning that they
they give me this
inductive capability which means that um
this is a shared edge edgewise mechanism
and does not depend on the graph
structure so it on the global graph
structure so it means i can transfer it
across the graphs so this function a is
transferable between graphs or from one
part of the graph
to the next part of the graph so these
are the benefits and kind of the
discussion
uh of the attention mechanism
to give you an example here is
um an example of a um
of a network uh called quora this is a
citation network of different papers
coming from different disciplines and
different
disciplines different publication
classes here are colored in different
colors and what we try to show here is
with
different edge thickness is the
attention score
between a pair of nodes i and j so it's
simply a normalized attention score by
basically saying
what's the attention of i to j and
what's the attention of
j to i across different layers
k notice that attentions
can be asymmetric right one message the
uh your message from you to me
might be very important while message
from me to you
for example might be less important so
the it doesn't have to be
uh symmetric and um
if you look at you know in terms of
improvements for example the graph
attention networks
can give you quite a bit of improvement
over let's say the
graph convolutional neural network uh
because
uh because of this attention mechanism
and allowing you to
learn what to focus uh what to focus on
and which subparts of the network to
learn from
so this is an example of graph attention
network how it learns attentions
and of course there has been many uh
upgrades
iterations of this idea of attention
on graph neural networks but the graph
attention network uh you know uh
two years ago was uh was the one that
first
developed and uh proposed that so um
this is
quite exciting so uh to summarize what
have we learned so far
we have learned that uh about classical
graph neural network layers and how they
are defined
and what kind of components do they
include
and they can often you know we can often
get better performance
by by combining different aspects
in terms of design and we can also
include as i will talk about later
other uh modern deep learning modules
into graph neural network design right
like for example we'll
i'm going to talk more about batch
normalization dropout
you can choose different activation
function attention
as well as aggregation so these are kind
of
transformations and components you can
choose to pick
um in order to design an effective
architecture
for your for your problem
so as i mentioned many kind of modern
deep learning modules or techniques can
be incorporated or generalized
to graph neural networks um there is a
like for example i'm going to talk about
next about batch normalization which
stabilizes
neural network training i'm going to
talk about the dropout
that allows us to prevent overfitting
we talked about attention to con
attention mechanism that controls the
importance of messages coming from
different parts of the neighborhood um
and we can also talk about skip
connections
uh and so on so um let me talk uh
about some of these concepts uh in a bit
more detail
so first i want to talk about the notion
of batch normalization
and the goal of batch normalization is
to stabilize
training of graph neural networks and
the idea is that given a batch of inputs
given a
batch of data points in our case a batch
of node embeddings
we want to re-center node embeddings to
zero min
and scale them to have unit variance
so to to be very precise what we mean by
this i'm given a set of inputs in our
case this will be vectors
of node embeddings i then can compute
what
uh for every coordinate what is the mean
value of that coordinate
and what is the variance along that
coordinate
of the vector uh across this n
uh input points uh x that are part of
our
of a mini batch and then um
i can also have um in this case i can
have
um uh um then uh
you know there is the input there is the
output that are the two
uh trainable parameters gamma uh and
beta
and then i can uh come up with the
output that is simply
um i take this inputs x i
standardize them in a sense that i
subtract the mean and divide by the
variance along that dimension so now
this x's have
zero mean and unit variance and then i
can further learn
how to transform them by basically
linearly transforming them by
multiplying with gamma
and adding a bias factor
uh bias term beta
and i do this independently for every
coordinate for every dimension
of every data point of every embedding i
that is in the mini batch so to
summarize
batch normalization stabilizes training
it first standardizes the data
so stand to standardize means subtract
the mean
divide by the uh by the standard
deviation so this means now
x has zero mean and variance of one
so unit variance and then i can also
learn
uh these parameters beta and gamma that
now linearly transform
x along each dimension and this is now
the output
of the batch normalization
the second technique i want to discuss
is called
dropout and the idea and what this
allows us to do in neural networks
is prevent overfitting and the idea is
that during
training with some small probability p
a random set of neurons will be set to
zero
um and uh during testing we are going to
use
all the neurons of the network so the
idea
is if you have a let's say fit forward
neural network
the idea is that some of the neurons you
set to zero
so that information out flows only
between the neurons that are not
set to zero and the idea here is that
this
forces the neural network to be more
robust
to corrupted data or to corrupted inputs
that's
uh the idea and because the neural
network is now more robust
you it prevents neural network from
overfitting
in a graph neural network dropout is
applied
to the linear layer in the message
function
so the idea is that when we take the
message
from node view from the previous layer
and we were multiplying it with this
matrix w here uh to this
linear layer to this w we can now apply
a dropout right rather than saying here
are the inputs
multiply with w to get the outputs m
you can now basically set some of the
parts
uh of the input uh as well as the output
uh to zero uh and this way mimic
uh the dropout that's the that's the
idea
and as i said in terms of dropout what
this does is
it helps with um preventing overfitting
of neural networks
the next uh component of a
graph neural network layer is in terms
of nonlinear
activation function um right and the
idea is that we apply this
activation to each dimension of the
of the embedding x what we can do is
apply a rectified linear unit uh which
is defined simply as the maximum of
x and zero so the way you can think of
it based on the input input x
the red line gives you the output so if
the x is negative
the output is 0 and if x is positive the
output is
x itself and this is most commonly used
activation function we can also apply
a sigmoid uh activation function a
sigmoid is defined here
here it's its shape so as a function of
the input
the output would be will be on value
zero to one
and this basically means that you can
take a x that
that has a domain from minus infinity to
plus infinity
and kind of transform it into something
to to the bounded
output from zero to one um and this is
used when you wanna restrict the range
of your embeddings when you want to
restrict the range of your output
and then what empirically works best is
called
parametric value and parametric value
is defined as the maximum of x and zero
plus
some trainable parameter alpha minimum
of
x and zero so this basically means
that empirically uh if x is greater than
zero
uh you output x itself and if it's less
than zero
you you output some x multiplied by some
coefficient
uh a in this case uh this is not
an attention weight this is a different
coefficient with train
and now the shape of the parametric
value
looks like i show here and empirically
this works better than
a value because you can train this
parameter
a so to summarize what we have discussed
and what we have learned so far
we talked about uh modern deep learning
modules that can be included into graph
neural network
layers to achieve even better
performance
we discussed about linear
transformations batch normalization uh
drop out uh different activation
functions and we also discussed
the uh attention mechanism as well as
different ways
uh then to aggregate uh the messages
if you wanna play with these different
architectural choices in an easy way we
have actually developed a package called
graph gym that basically allows you to
very quickly and easily try out
and test out different design choices uh
to find the one
that works best on your individual
uh problem so if you click this this is
a link it will
lead you to github and you can play
with this code to see how different
design choices make
a practical difference to your own
application
or use case